<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-manycouches-completely-remote-meetings-00">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private=""?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="Thoughts on Completely Remote Meetings">Initial Thoughts on Completely Remote IETF Meetings</title>

<author initials="D." surname="York" fullname="Dan York">
<organization></organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Keene, NH</city>
<code></code>
<country>USA</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>york@isoc.org</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2016" month="October" day="31"/>

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>Manycouches</workgroup>


<abstract>
<t>This document captures initial thoughts about having IETF meetings that
are completely virtual. It explores the issues involved with both a
&quot;planned&quot; virtual meeting and an &quot;emergency&quot; virtual meeting.
</t>
</abstract>


</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>What would a &quot;completely virtual&quot; IETF meeting look like? What would be
issues? What would be the advantages? How could it work?
</t>
<t>The &quot;manycouches&quot; design team was convened to explore these issues and
understand what might be involved in holding a completely virtual meeting.
On 20 July 2017, members met with the IESG for a joint discussion at the
IETF 96 meeting in Berlin. This document outlines many of the key issues and questions for discussion that emerged out of that Berlin meeting as well as
mailing list conversations.
</t>
<t>Discussions identified two types of potential meetings the IETF could have
that would be completely virtual:
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>PLANNED VIRTUAL MEETING - A &quot;regular&quot; meeting of the IETF that would be planned to be completely virtual.</t>
<t>EMERGENCY VIRTUAL MEETING - There could be a situation where a planned physical meeting suddenly needs to be virtual due to physical or political situations. For example, a natural disaster shortly before a meeting might cause people to not be able to attend.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Tools and processes may be very similar between the two types of meetings.
A key difference is that for an &quot;emergency&quot; meeting there may be the desire to
replicate the planned schedule of the physical meeting as closely as possible.
</t>
<t>It is unclear if the IETF might ever choose to hold a planned virtual meeting,
but this document is designed to facilitate the discussion around what that
might look like.
</t>

<section anchor="benefits" title="Benefits">
<t>Proponents of planned virtual meetings point to benefits such as:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>No requirement to travel, removing an economic issue for many.</t>
<t>All participants are on an equal footing (versus current situation where physical participants have more interaction capability than remote attendees).</t>
<t>Ability to think differently about how the schedule of the meeting might look.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The sections below outline many of the questions and ideas, some of which may
be benefits.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="challenges" title="Challenges">
<t>There are many challenges with hosting a completely virtual meeting. Some key
issues are:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Inability to have the &quot;high bandwidth&quot; conversations enabled by face-to-face meetings.</t>
<t>No ability to have &quot;hallway conversations&quot; and casual meetings with other participants.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The remainder of the document outlines many of the challenges and associated
questions.
</t>
<t>Several participants voiced the opinion that replacing a physical meeting would
be pretty much impossible.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="conventions-and-terminology" title="Conventions and Terminology">
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
<t>Additionally, the key words &quot;<spanx style="strong">MIGHT</spanx>&quot;, &quot;<spanx style="strong">COULD</spanx>&quot;, &quot;<spanx style="strong">MAY WISH TO</spanx>&quot;, &quot;<spanx style="strong">WOULD
PROBABLY</spanx>&quot;, &quot;<spanx style="strong">SHOULD CONSIDER</spanx>&quot;, and &quot;<spanx style="strong">MUST (BUT WE KNOW YOU WON'T)</spanx>&quot; in
this document are to interpreted as described in RFC 6919 <xref target="RFC6919"/>.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="program" title="Program">

<section anchor="meeting-structure" title="Meeting Structure">
<t>With a completely virtual meeting, the structure of the meeting does not
have to comply with the traditional IETF meeting schedule. It could, for
instance, stretch out over the entire 24 hours of a day. Questions for
discussion include:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Is the meeting still structured over a week?</t>
<t>Do the meetings still exist within certain hours?</t>
<t>Do multiple meetings exist at the same time as they do now?</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Again, in the case of an unplanned &quot;emergency&quot; virtual meeting the desire
may be to stick with the already-planned schedule. But for a planned
virtual meeting the schedule can be open for discussion.
</t>
<t>There was some discussion that a meeting could span more than the
traditional week. However, the counterpoint is that keeping it within
a week gives a focused block of time that people could allocate for
participation in the virtual event.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="timezones" title="Timezones">
<t>What timezone does a virtual meeting operate in? Or does it operate in
multiple timezones?
</t>
<t>One suggestion was that each working group might choose its own timezone
based on the best timezone for the main contributors and leaders. (Although
this might then limit participation from other areas of the world.)
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="deadlines" title="Deadlines">
<t>What do deadlines look like for a completely virtual meeting? Are the
deadlines for agendas and drafts kept as they are for a regular meeting?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="plenaries" title="Plenaries">
<t>What does a plenary look like in a virtual meeting? The same large session
as today?
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="user-journey--experience" title="User Journey / Experience">

<section anchor="participating-in-multiple-sessions" title="Participating in multiple sessions">
<t>It is currently possible for remote participants to join into multiple
working group sessions at the same time. Users simply run Meetecho in
multiple browser windows or multiple computers. How does this impact
users' experience?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="side-meetings" title="Side meetings">
<t>It is quite common for groups to decide during an IETF meeting to go
off and have a side meeting.
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>How can this capability be reproduced in a virtual environment?</t>
<t>Could the system allow people to create ad hoc meetings in some fashion?</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="hallway-conversations" title="Hallway conversations">
<t>The casual hallway conversations are a key component of IETF physical
meetings. How can some version of this capacity be made available?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="unstructured-time" title="Unstructured time">
<t>How do you incorporate some concept of &quot;unstructured&quot; time where people
can meet and connect?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="serendipity--discovering-other-users" title="Serendipity - discovering other users">
<t>Part of a physical meeting involves discovering other people with common
interests or backgrounds. How do you help people find others?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="microphone-lines" title="Microphone lines">
<t>How do &quot;mic lines&quot; work in a completely virtual meeting? Would this in fact
be a benefit as all attendees would be in the same queue?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="mentoring" title="Mentoring">
<t>How would the &quot;mentor&quot; program work in a virtual meeting? The same as with
a physical meeting?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="inclusivity" title="Inclusivity">
<t>How do you bring new people into sessions? How do people learn about side meetings?
About hallway conversations?
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="technical-considerations" title="Technical Considerations">
<t>Many technical questions need to be discussed.
</t>

<section anchor="infrastructure" title="Infrastructure">
<t>What is the infrastructure used to host a completely virtual meeting?
Are current systems such as Meetecho sufficient? Would new infrastructure
need to be established?
</t>
<t>What kind of bandwidth would need to be available?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="capabilities" title="Capabilities">
<t>Do virtual attendees have video connections? voice? chat?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="network-operation-center-noc" title="Network Operation Center (NOC)">
<t>Where does the NOC &quot;exist&quot; for a completly virtual meeting? What is its role?
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="administrative" title="Administrative">

<section anchor="centralized-resources" title="Centralized Resources">
<t>What is the impact of a virtual meeting on centralized resources such as
support staff? What is the full role of the Secretariat during the meeting?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="finances" title="Finances">
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>What would the impact be on IETF finances?</t>
<t>Would we charge the same amount to attendees as a regular meeting?</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>There are many considerations related to security and privacy that need
to be factored in to a virtual meeting.
</t>

<section anchor="availability" title="Availability">
<t>How do we ensure that an attack such as a distributed denial of service (DDoS) doesn't take out the entire virtual meeting? What about an attack against a
particular region?
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="integrity" title="Integrity">
<t>How do you know that the person who is logged into whatver system is
used is in fact who they say they are? In a physical meeting:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>We can see the person and physically identify them.</t>
<t>Users wear name badges that were issued at registration time.</t>
<t>There are typically other people who may know many individuals.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>How are these physical considerations replicated in a virtual meeting?
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>There are no IANA considerations associated with this document.
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6919.xml"?>
</references>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>The author thanks all of the participants of the manycouches design
team as well as the IESG members who participated in the discussion
on 20 July 2016 at IETF 96 in Berlin.
</t>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>
